Welcome back to AM Northwest. Knowing how to do
it right could save you big on your next garage
sale or secondhand store shopping spree.
Here to share tips on how to barter like a pro,
we welcome back antique appraiser Gary Germer.
Good to have you with us again.
Thank you, Helen. Thanks for being here.
Now, when we talk about bartering, you're
not a big fan of it, doing it yourself.
No, well, I'm on the opposite side of
it, running estate sales regularly,
and so you do all this
work to get it set up.
I guess I'm a communist at heart. I put the
best price, everybody gets a chance to buy it,
and let's be done with it.
But that's just not how the system works.
Right, but you say the most important
thing is to follow the golden rule.
It is. I think a lot of the TV shows that have
come out give this idea that you're supposed
to be ruthless,
and it's a challenge of wits between
people, and that's only half right.
I think that it's really,
if you're kind to somebody.
You want to give a deal to your friend.
Sure.
If someone treats you badly,
you want to show them the road.
Right.
And so if you're nice to people and
you ask politely, can you take less?
Is this your best price?
Right.
Could you take this much? And
respect them, respect the item.
The idea that acting, talking the item down,
that it's a piece of junk, that's somebody.
That doesn't help you any.
Well, I just feel like, well, obviously you
shouldn't buy it because you're much too good to
own something as terrible as this.
So I'm good at it.
I just don't.
So be kind. That's the number one thing.
That's the number one thing. Be respectful
and don't be unreasonable with people.
You say always ask for a discount.
Always ask. There's so many
times I have people who don't.
On the opposite end, you have the people who go
all the time and are really ruthless about it.
On the other hand, there's some people
who just, it's not in our nature.
You don't go to Fred Meyer and try to get a
discount on eggs and what if I only bought seven
and all that.
We're not used to it.
Right.
So just sometimes.
Just asking.
Go ahead.
Never hurts to ask.
If they won't do it,
don't take it personally.
And how do you ask?
What do you ask?
You ask politely.
Say, well, Ken, is this your best price?
Can you take this for it?
Never offer less than half
of what somebody has on it.
Oh, good point.
Never offer less than half.
Because that's considered an insult.
It's just rude.
Yeah.
Look at the audience and what time it is.
If it's a shop, they're going to be more invested
in their prices than people who are having
a garage sale who want
to just get rid of it.
Their goals get away.
You should.
You say to the seller,
never take it personally.
Culturally, and this is something I have to
admit, my staff pulls me away from the till every
now and then because
I start getting upset.
I got to remind myself of this
because I start getting mad.
What makes you upset?
Well, oftentimes, this
is a cultural thing.
Oftentimes, people who are first generation
to our country and in their country,
they just like, for instance, in the
Chinese culture, bartering ruthlessly.
You have $10.
I'll give you $1.
And they're just relentless.
And it took me the longest time to realize that
culturally, they don't mean to be insulting.
That's how it's done.
Right.
But it comes across in our
culture as being very rude.
So culturally, there can be ways that people
take it, that people barter that can be taken.
So if you're a seller,
don't take it personally.
Don't take it personally.
And you can't sell it for that,
then just can't sell it for that.
Right.
The power of silence.
What does that mean?
Well, that comes as a basic in
any kind of negotiation you learn.
Once you've made an offer,
can you take $50 for this?
Shut up.
And the next person who speaks loses.
And so you have to let them.
And sometimes it can
be an awkward silence.
My friend fills it in,
who's a terrific barterer.
He fills it in with cow noises.
Mmm, $50.
Mmm, mmm, mmm.
You know, these two people are
making cow noises at each other.
I want to stab myself
in the eyes with this.
I can see how that helps
you just not say something.
Yeah.
And so then let the person respond.
Right.
And don't get nervous.
So the power of just being silent.
Make your offer and then just
be comfortable being silent.
Okay, here's something I did not.
If you want to take a sip of water.
Okay, never hold on to an item you're
bartering for, which is an interesting tactic.
Yeah.
And if you're selling it,
make them hold on to it.
Now, this is, if you're holding on to
it, you're emotionally attached to it.
And it puts you in a position
where, you know, you're hugging it.
The person who you're bartering with.
Knows you want it.
And it's showing way too much interest.
Whereas on the conversely, if you're selling
it to somebody, have them hold it while you're
talking to them.
And then that you're hoping
then they get more attached.
They don't want to put it down.
And that is a good one.
I've never heard of that before.
Yeah, that's that.
That works.
Okay.
Cash is king.
Now that seems obvious.
What you want.
What I mean by that is you want to be sure
to make it easy for the seller to sell.
Usually those of us running a state sale.
Or someone's running a garage sale.
We've got to clear the house out.
So if you want to buy the sofa
and you want to buy the piano.
And then you want me, you
want to give me a deposit.
And you want me to come on
my day off to meet you later.
And can I help them lift the other
end of the piano and take it away.
And then somebody else
comes along offers me less.
But they'll take it away immediately.
Right.
The less price and less hassle.
So if you the more easy
you make it for the person.
They'll take a smaller price.
If they don't have to
hassle with the hassle.
So use your cash and
make it easy for them.
So pick it up.
Take it away.
Give me a don't don't
make a drama out of it.
Don't do layaway and payment plans.
Just do it.
Be prepared and be educated.
Yeah, this is a good one because a
lot of people barter by offering half.
They don't know what it's worth.
But they'll give you half.
Whatever you're asking.
They'll give you half.
Now you and we talk about
this among ourselves.
The dealers that if I had a $10
bill and I put it out for $5.
Well, they're not going to buy it unless
I give it to him for 250, you know.
Oh, right.
But if they if I have it for
20, well, they'll give me 10.
They'll give you 10.
For 10.
And so if you got an item you need to know what
it's worth is to know where they have a good
deal.
If there's a solid if it's a if it's a gold
necklace and the person doesn't realize it and they
priced it as costume jewelry.
Don't sit and barter with them.
But you've know something that they
don't need and just take it and buy it.
Right.
All good tips.
Gary.
Thank you very much.
We'll put the information on our website.
At kat.com.